A Finding Aid to the Eve Propp Papers Regarding Joseph Cornell, 1966-1994, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Eve Propp papers regarding Joseph Cornell
1966-1994
Archives of American Art
Propp, Eve
Cornell, Joseph
AAA.propeve
Archival Resource Key
1 Linear foot
The Eve Propp papers regarding artist Joseph Cornell date from 1966-1994 and measure 1 linear foot. This small collection documents the relationship between Eve Propp, a gallerist, and Joseph Cornell. The two maintained a friendship through frequent letters and visits. The papers consist of approximately sixty letters from Cornell to Propp from 1968-1972, letters from others, notes on Propp's visits to Cornell, printed material, and photographic material.
Scope and Contents
The Eve Propp papers regarding artist Joseph Cornell date from 1966-1994 and measure 1 linear foot. This small collection documents the relationship between Eve Propp, a gallerist, and Joseph Cornell. The two maintained a friendship through frequent letters and visits. The papers consist of approximately sixty letters from Cornell to Propp from 1968-1972, letters from others, notes on Propp's visits to Cornell, printed material, and photographic material.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as a single series.
Series 1: Eve Propp papers regarding Joseph Cornell, 1966-1994 (1 linear foot; Box 1)
Biographical / Historical
Eve Propp befriended artist Joseph Cornell (1903-1972) while operating a short lived gallery in New York, N.Y. She visited him at his home on Wednesdays from 1969-1970. She now resides in upstate New York.
Conditions Governing Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated to the Archives of American Art in 2017 by Eve Propp.
Related Materials
Also found in the Archives of American Art are the Joseph Cornell papers. The bulk of Cornell's source material resides in the Joseph Cornell Study Center, Smithsonian American Art Museum, along with his library and record collection.
Assemblage artists -- New York (State) -- New York; Filmmakers -- New York (State) -- New York; Gallery owners -- New York (State) -- New York
- Eve Propp papers regarding Joseph Cornell, 1966-1994; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 1 Linear foot Box 1
  Scope and Contents
  Approximately sixty letters or cards from Cornell to Eve Propp often incorporate collages, puzzles, and objects. One file contains a few objects that have become separated from the letters. Other letters here are from Cornell's sister, lawyers involved with the estate following Cornell's death, a handwriting expert, and museum curators.
  Propp's notes document topics Cornell discussed during their visits, including his thoughts about the color blue, his mother's strictness, the anxiety he felt as a student at Andover, among other topics.
  Printed material collected by Propp about Cornell includes a calendar from 1969, the year they were in most frequent contact; clippings from magazines and newspapers; and exhibition announcements and catalogs.
  Several photographs of Cornell taken in 1969 during one of Propp's visits are included here with the original negatives, and several copy prints made in subsequent decades.
  - Letters from Joseph Cornell, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters from Joseph Cornell, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters from Joseph Cornell, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3-8)
  - Letters from Joseph Cornell, 1970-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Objects from Joseph Cornell Letters, circa 1968-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Empty Envelopes from Joseph Cornell Letters, 1968-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Letters from Others, circa 1969-1994; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Notes, circa 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Printed Material, Archival Resource Key (Box 1)
    - Calendar, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Clippings, 1966-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, circa 1970-1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Photographs and Negatives, 1994; 1982; 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)